Amelia Taylor

Bend, OR ajt@ameliajtaylor.com www.linkedin.com/in/ameliajtaylor Home: (719) 287-8978 ameliajtaylor.github.io github.com/ameliajtaylor

I'm a data scientist whose first career was Tenured Mathematics Professor. I love working on complex problems with clear business impact. As a data scientist, I deliver complex data products requiring a deep understanding of statistics, design of experiments, and machine learning along with an the ability to balance the trade-offs between research into the best solution and delivery of a quality product on time. As a Staff Data Scientist, I love leading technical delivery teams, thinking about strategy and evaluating ROI early in a project to inform prioritization.

Skills & Languages Summary: Python, Pandas, NumPy, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib, Altair, Plotnine, R, tidyverse, ggplot, Binderhub, Jupyter, Git, SQL, Mode, Looker Studio, dbt*, Snowflake*, Flask*, Docker*, Jenkins*

*some experience

Experience:

• Staff Data Scientist, Shopify, Bend, OR

February 2022 - Present

Shopify is a commerce platform for merchants, making commerce better for everyone.

- Lead design and analysis of the largest and most complex experiment in 2023. Built trust with business partners in the experimental plan through simulation and consistent clear communication.
- Drive improvements to the experiments platform through collaboration with data scientists and platform development team.
- Consult on experimental design and analysis across the organization.
- Deliver high impact short term analytical solutions in the commerce space leveraging industry standard metrics and segmentation.

• Staff Data Scientist, Zymergen, Inc, Bend, OR

July 2019 - January 2022

Zymergen integrated robotics, software and genetic engineering, all guided by data science, to deliver end-to-end microbial strain improvement for applications in industrial fermentation.

- Worked with C-suite and director level leadership to scope projects and determine ROI, providing the technical expertise to make quick go no-go decisions.
- Technical lead of two different cross-functional teams that delivered multiple products on time with a unique blend of statistics, chemical engineering and software engineering mix. Throughout these deliveries we standardized processes, captured critical data, and cut data processing time by at least a day per month.
- Coordinated across diverse stakeholders from a broad range of scientists to data engineering, and manufacturing.
- Architected complex deliveries including quick turn around UI connected to libraries integrated into our continuous integration system.
- Delivered high impact short term analytical solutions.

• Data Science Manager, Zymergen, Inc, Bend, OR

March 2019 - July 2019

- Facilitated transition of data science team from a small number of people working on individual projects to a large org delivering on complex products using cross-functional teams.
- Coached data scientists stretching into project management and technical leadership.
- Helped onboard two new managers.

• Senior Data Scientist, Zymergen, Inc, Bend, OR

January 2019 - July 2019

- Built product for assay development that cut analytical time by 70%, made experiments and analysis repeatable
 and designed and stored data for improved analysis and future predictive models.
- Technical lead for cross-functional collaborative product team.

- Provided analytical support for client teams doing assay development. Technical lead for team that developed the proof of concept that lead to assay development tool.
- Owned end-to-end development of outlier detection from algorithm development to automation of the process. Automation save 2 hours per week per client. Model selection and hyper-parameter tuning algorithms provided metrics critical for rigorous decision making. Patent pending and presented at PyBay https://youtu.be/gOSz5SFJAI4.
- Designed and and worked cross-functionally to productionize normalized data tables storing data critical to the data science team that is now used company wide and considered critical infrastructure.
- Consultant, Mathematical Sciences Research Institute, Bend, OR

October 2017 - December 2018

 Conducted study of postdoctoral fellowship program analyzing seven years of data. Updated existing survey to adhere to current best practices and analyzed results in R as primary author of the final report.

• Consultant, Insight Data Science, Seattle, WA

September - November, 2017

- Taught probability course and mentored fellows in technical development of products and interview preparation.

• University Professor

Instructor, Oregon State University - Cascades, Bend, OR

September 2015 - June 2016

- Associate Professor (tenured), Colorado College, Colorado Springs, CO

July 2012 - May 2016

- Assistant Professor (tenure-track), Colorado College, Colorado Springs, CO

August 2006 - July 2012

- Assistant Professor (tenure-track), St. Olaf College, Northfield, MN

August 2003 - July 2006

- VIGRE Hill Assistant Professor (postdoctoral fellow), Rutgers University, Piscataway, NJ

2000-2003

- Leadership
 - * Supervised 11 full time faculty, 7 part time faculty and 2 staff. (Department Chair)
 - * Coordinated all daily operations of the department, including two major personnel reviews, an external review of the department, course scheduling, weekly speaker series and budgeting process. (Department Chair)
 - * Coordinated department assessment team for two years. Developed outcomes, rubrics and feedback loops.
 - * Organized 6 intense week-long workshops of 25+ people.
- Data Science
 - * Developed a statistically powerful method for inferring phylogenetic trees using representation theory. Implemented algorithm for inference and simulation data tests in R.
 - * Converted Statistical Modeling and Probability Theory course to being taught using R.
 - * Developed and published an algorithm for computing a monomial ideal invariant using reverse search.
 - * Developed a Monte Carlo based method for fast computation of a key invariant in commutative algebra.

Open Source Code Contributions:

- Statsmodels python package
 - Add the Games-Howell statistical test (in review)
 - Two bugs in the code to compute the student's quantile distribution. (in review, Bug 1 link, Bug 2 link).

Professional Presentations:

• Data Did That! 2019 Fall Gordon Lecturer, Denison University

October 2019

• Data Did That! National Mathematics Festival, Washington DC

May 2019

• Robots, Biology and Unsupervised Model Selection, San Francisco, CA

August 2018

Education:

• Ph.D., Mathematics, University of Kansas, Lawrence, KS

May 2000

• M.S., Mathematics, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN

May 1997

• **B.A., Mathematics**, *St. Olaf College*, Northfield, MN Magna Cum Laude, with Distinction

May 1994